Register of the Joaquin Maurin Papers, 1870-1976
Hoover Institution Archives
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1915-1973
  - Grant, Frances. See Inter-American Association for Democracy and Freedom
  - Grossi-Mier, Manuel, 1972-1973 (including literature of the Partido Socialista Obrero Espanol). See also BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, Condolences sent to JM
  - Guehenno, Jean (Europe, Editions Rieder, Paris), 1932-1936
  - Guibert, Yves, 1961-1962
  - Gutman, Bob, 1951-1968. See also BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, Condolences sent to JM
  - Guzman, Mario, 1964-1973
  - Habaru, A., 1928
  - Hall, Florence, 1964
  - Haya de la Torre, Victor Raul, 1929
  - Henson, Francis A., (The Marxist Quarterly, N.Y.,), 1936
  - Hernandez Zancajo, Carlos, 1935
  - Hidalgo, Diego, 1928-1960
  - Hispanic Society of America, N.Y. (Adelaide M. Meyer). See also Huntington, Archer M.
  - Hook, Sidney, 1949
  - Humbert-Droz, Jules. See Communist International, Secretariat
  - Hunt, J. Christopher, 1967
  - Huntington, Archer M., 1954-1955
  - Huxley, Aldous, 1959-1960
  - Ibanez, Roberto. See SUBJECT FILE, Hungary
  - Iduarte, Andres, n.d.
  - Iglesias, Ignacio, 1953-1963. See also Cuadernos and BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, Condolences sent to JM
  - Iglesias, Ramon -cousin of Maurin-, 1936. See also BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, Visa and Naturalization process, Correspondence of JM and SUBJECT FILE, Maurin, Jeanne, Correspondence
  - Independent Labour Party, London, 1936. See also SUBJECT FILE, Maurin, Jeanne, Correspondence
  - Institute of International Labor Research, Inc., N.Y. See Volman, Sacha
  - Inter-American Association for Democracy and Freedom, N.Y., 1957-1973
  - The Irish Worker, Dublin (Jim Larkin), 1931
  - Iturrioz, Jose (Avicena, Barcelona), 1952-1956
  - Izvestia, Moscow, 1928
  - James Cunningham, Son & Co., N.Y., 1948
  - Janes, Jose, 1947-1949 (including correspondence of his wife, Ester Nadal, 1959 )
  - Jauregui Hurtado, Arturo. See Organizacion Regional Interamericana de Trabajadores
  - John Bean Manufacturing Company, Lansing, Mich., 1948
  - Juan Ferres y Hermano, Barcelona, 1950
  - Julia, Jaime (Columbia Pictures International Corporation, N.Y.), 1949-1950
  - Just, Julio, 1962-1969 (including articles of Just and the message of the President of the Cortes of the Spanish Government in exile, Mexico, 1963 )
  - Kairis, Robert A., 1964-1965
  - Kantor, Harry, 1960-1970
  - Kent, Victoria (Iberica, N.Y.), 1956-1969. See also BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, Condolences sent to JM
  - Kilbom, Karl, 1934 (including issues of the Folkets Dagblad, Stockholm, which published some of Maurin's articles)
  - Kohl, Hermann J., 1951-1953
  - Lafuente, A., 1966
  - Lahoz, Adoracion -wife of Saturnino Carod-, 1952-1958
  - Lajara, Sanz, 1962
  - Lana-Sarrate, C., 1951
  - Languas, J. A., 1957
  - Lardo Cuneo, 1936
  - Larrea, Gustavo, 1956-1968
  - Lautier Fils, Inc., N.Y., 1949-1951. See also Collado Herrero, Jose (Box 7)
  - Lazarevitch, N. See BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, Condolences sent to JM
  - Lazitch, Branco, 1963-1966. See also Guibert, Yves
  - Leighton, Charles H., 1959-1972 (including two of his essays on Casona)
  - Leon Treso, Francisco, 1954
  - Lemos, Percy M., 1958-1959
  - Levitas, S. M., (The New Leader, N.Y.), 1948-1960
  - Llopis, Rodolfo, 1929-1954
  - Llorens, Carmen, 1961
  - Llorens Castillo, Vicente, 1966-1972 (including a resume of Maurin). See also Tierno Galvan, Enrique
  - Lopez, Juan (CNT, Mexico), 1956
  - Lorton de Ramos, Henni, 1958
  - Losada, Jorge (The Latin American Times, N.Y.) 1965
  - Lovestone, Jay, 1934
  - Lozovsky, Alexander (Secretary, Profintern), 1928
  - Lundquist, Darrel W., 1969
  - Luque, Juan Jose, 1947
  - Luter, John, 1963
  - McCampbell & Company, N.Y., 1949. See also Collado Herrero, Jose
  - McDonald, Nancy. See Spanish Refugee Aid, Inc., N.Y.
  - McDonough, J. J. See General Motors Corporation
  - Macia, Francesco (Generalitat de Catalunya), 1931
  - Madariaga, Salvador de, 1954-1972. See also BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, Condolences sent to JM and Visa and Naturalization process, Correspondence of JM
  - Manach, Jorge. See SUBJECT FILE, Hungary
  - Manzano, Cesar, 1955-1968. See also BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, Condolences sent to JM
  - Marichal, Juan, 1956-1970
  - Marimon Cairol, Joseph, 1972
  - Marin, Miguel A., 1966-1973
  - Marquez, Antonio, 1959
  - Marti Jara, Enrique, 1930-1961
  - Martin de Alvarez, Christina -daughter of Arsenio Martin, for whom see BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, Letters of support to Maurin-, 1958-1966. See also BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, Obituaries
  - Martinet, Marcel (Editions Rieder, Paris), 1932
  - Martinez Barrio, Diego, 1947-1960. See also BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, Visa and Naturalization process, Documents submitted and SUBJECT FILE, Maurin, Jeanne, Correspondence
  - Martinez Feduchy, Manuel, 1956
  - Martinez Garcia, Manolo, 1948-1958
  - Martinez de Utiel, C. A., 1969
  - Masferrer, Lorenzo, 1953-1957. See also BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, Condolences sent to JM and SUBJECT FILE, Bloque Obrero y Campesino, 1st Congress
  - Mata, Andres, 1957-1964
  - Matteo, Ivan and Maria Lombardo, n.d.
  - Maura, Miguel, 1964 (including correspondence with his grandson, Joaquin Romero Maura)
  - Maurin, Maria -sister of Maurin-, 1967-1972
  - Maurin, Mario -son of Maurin-, 1967 (including a resume of Mario Maurin)
  - Meaker, Gerald H., 1963-1965
  - Medrano, Humberto, 1961-1966
  - Menendez, Aquilino Moral, 1959-1972. See also SUBJECT FILE, Gibraltar
  - Meyer, Hakon, 1934
  - Meziat, Enrique, 1934
  - Miller, Arthur, 1950
  - Mir Porte, Rafael, 1965
  - Miravittles, Jaume (Martin W. de Soto), 1928-1964. See also BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, Condolences sent to JM, Obituaries and Visa and Naturalization process, Correspondence of JM and Documents submitted
  - Miro, Fidel, 1963-1966
  - Molina, Juan M., 1969
  - Monge Alfaro, Carlos. See SUBJECT FILE, Hungary
  - Monteiro de Castro, Livia Santos, 1968
  - Montejo, Maria Lilia, 1954-1958
  - Montezuma Hurtado, Alberto, 1967 (including some of his articles)
  - Moreno, Mario (Cantinflas), 1955-1971
  - Morodo, Raul, 1973
  - Mosquera, Marta, 1965
  - Moulines, Linus, 1947-1973. See also BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, Condolences sent to JM
  - Movimiento de Accion Sindical, New York Delegation, 1960
  - Munoz Abad, J. (Ateneo de Madrid), 1931
  - Munoz Marin, Luis, 1950-1962
  - Nanita, Abelardo R. (hijo), 1965
  - The Nation, N.Y., 1954
  - The New York Public Library, n.d.
  - The New York Times, 1959. See also SUBJECT FILE, El Campesino
  - Nieto, Jose, 1953
  - Nin, Andres, 1928-1931. See also SUBJECT FILE, Maurin, Jeanne, Correspondence
  - Nonoyama, Minoko, 1971-1973
  - Norda Essential Oils Company, N.Y., 1950
  - Nunez, Benjamin, 1954-1962. See also SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, Post-1948, Course on political ideologies given at the Institute of Political Education in San Jose, Costa Rica and SUBJECT FILE, Stevenson, Adlai
  - Nunez, Enrique (Replica, Puerto Rico), 1972
  - Nunez Arca, Pascual, 1959 (including his resume and articles of his)
  - Olalquiaga, Caridad. See Aguado-Andreut, Salvador
  - Olivar-Bertrand, R., 1962-1973 (including his resume)
  - Olivares, Delgado, 1956
  - Onis, Federico de, 1949-1953. See also BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, Visa and Naturalization process, Documents submitted
  - L'Opinio, Barcelona, 1928 (including a questionnaire to which Maurin answered -on Spanish politics)
  - Orfila Reynal, Arnaldo. See SUBJECT FILE, Hungary (Box 8)
  - Organizacion Regional Interamericana de Trabajadores, Mexico, 1962 (including articles of Arturo Jauregui Hurtado, Secretary-General)
  - Organization of American States, W.,D.C., 1956
  - Orlich, Francisco J., 1962-1963
  - Ortega y Gasset, Eduardo, 1957
  - Ortega y Gasset, Jose, 1952
  - Ortiz, Eloy, 1959 (including one article of his)
  - Overseas News Agency, 1949-1950
  - Pachter, Mrs. Henry (Henri Rabasseire), 1967
  - Pages, Mariona -sister of Pedro Pages-, 1949-1953
  - Pages, Pedro (Victor Alba). See also BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, Obituaries
    - 1947-1959 (including articles of Victor Alba on Guatemala and Largo Caballero, 1954 )
    - 1960-1974 (including a letter to the editor concerning the P.O.U.M., 1964 )
  - Pane, Josep, 1953-1972. See also BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, Condolences sent to JM
  - Parajou, Mario. See BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, Condolences sent to JM
  - Pareja Diezcanseco, Alfredo, 1961. See SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, Post-1948, Course on political ideologies given at the Institute of Political Education in San Jose, Costa Rica
  - Pares, Francisco, 1962-1963
  - Partido Obrero de Unificacion Marxista (P.O.U.M.), Paris, 1947-1973 (including newsletters)
  - Pascual Mora, Ramon, 1961
  - Pasion, Antonio de la, 1949
  - Payne, Stanley, 1960-1971. See also BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, Condolences sent to JM
  - Pego, Aurelio, 1951-1971
  - Pellicena Camacho, Pedro, 1958-1959
  - Perez Castro, Ismael -father of Ismael Perez Perasso, Carlos Perez Perasso and Elena Perez de Griem-, 1958-1959
  - Perez de Griem, Elena, 1959
  - Perez Perasso, Carlos, 1954-1961
  - Perez Perasso, Ismael, 1952-1962
  - Perez Sarmiento, Guillermo, 1958-1963
  - Perez Solis, Oscar, 1924-1951. See also BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, Letters of support to Maurin
  - Perez Vicente, Manuel, 1952
  - Le Peuple, Brussels, 1934
  - Picasso, Pablo, 1965
  - Picon Salas, Mariano. See SUBJECT FILE, Hungary
  - Pifarre, Roque, 1956
  - Pijoan, Jose, 1930-1955 (including an essay of his on Caravaggio)
  - Pina, Francisco. See Araquistain, Luis
  - Pineda de Castro, Alvaro, 1962
  - Piquer Mor, F., 1953
  - Le Populaire, Paris, 1934
  - Portas, Rafael E. (Sindicato de Trabajadores de la Produccion Cinematografica, Mexico), 1954
  - Portela, Luis, 1948-1973 (including a long manuscript of Portela on the origins of the communist party in Spain). See also BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, Obituaries
  - Poseidon, Buenos Aires, 1949-1950
  - PRADESA (Productos Agricolas y Derivados, S.A.), Barcelona, 1947-1950
  - Prewett, Virginia (The Latin American Times, N.Y.), 1965 (Box 9)
  - Prieto, Indalecio, 1948
  - Prieto, Tomas, 1968
  - Puente, Isaac, 1929
  - Pujol Font, Joan Luis, 1931
  - Putzeys, Guillermo A., 1965
  - Quer Torrent, Joan, 1960
  - Rabasseire, Henri. See Pachter, Mrs. Henry
  - Racaj Montemayor, Jose A. See BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, Condolences sent to JM
  - Raditsa, Bogdan, 1958
  - Radunsky, Ines, 1961-1965
  - Ramira Gomez, Vicente, 1948-1950
  - Ramos, Henri L., 1958
  - Ravines, Eudocio, 1929-1970
  - Rebull, Daniel (David Rey), 1948-1958. See also BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, Letters of support to Maurin, Condolences sent to JM and SUBJECT FILE, Maurin, Jeanne, Correspondence
  - Redondo, Susana, 1951-1952
  - Reina, Antonio, 1954-1959. See also BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, Visa and Naturalization process, Documents submitted
  - La Revolution Proletarienne, Paris, 1932
  - Rey, David. See Rebull, Daniel
  - Reyes, Alfonso, 1956-1959. See also SUBJECT FILE, Hungary
  - Reyes, Manuela M. de -related to Alfonso Reyes-, 1960-1962
  - Rio, Angel and Amelia del Rio (The Hispanic Institute in the United States, Columbia University), 1954-1964. See also Garcia Lorca de los Rios, Laura
  - Rios, Fernando de los, 1947. See also BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, Visa and Naturalization process, Correspondence of JM and Documents submitted
  - Roa, Raul. See SUBJECT FILE, Hungary
  - Robles, Emmanuel, 1968
  - Robles Piquer, Eduardo, 1968 (including his resume; an article on, and a caricature of, Arturo Illia)
  - Rocabert, Juan, 1958-1972. See also BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, Condolences sent to JM
  - Rodrigues, Jesus, 1960
  - Rodriguez, Enrique, 1948-1952
  - Rodriguez, Ramon, 1968
  - Rojas, Ricardo. See SUBJECT FILE, Hungary
  - Romero, Luis, 1965
  - Romero Maura, Joaquin, 1964-1965
  - Rosarios, Ottocar, 1965
  - Ross, Stanley, 1963 (including an article of his and one on him by Mitchel Levitas)
  - Rossi, Angelo, 1951
  - Roure-Dupont, Inc., N.Y., 1950
  - Roviralta, Jose Maria, 1948-1949
  - Rubia Barcia, Jose, 1970
  - Ruiz, Pablo (El Amigo del Pueblo, Paris) and Jaime Balius, 1962
  - Saborit Colomer, Andres, 1953. See also El Socialista, Paris
  - Samblancat, Angel, 1915-1930
  - Sanchez, Manolo, 1948-1973. See also BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, Condolences sent to JM
  - Sanchez Roca, Mariano, 1949
  - Santos, Eduardo, 1953-1966
  - Santovenia, Emeterio S., 1960
  - Sarda Llorens, Rafael, 1949-1973. See also BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, Condolences sent to JM
  - Sarradell, Enrique (El Pais, Lerida), 1928
  - Sawa, Takaaki, 1969-1973. See also BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, Condolences sent to JM
  - Sax, Ernie and Eithne, 1950-1969
  - Scottdale Mills, Georgia, 1949
  - Senador Gomez, Julio, 1917
  - Sender, Ramon J. See also BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, Visa and Naturalization process, Documents submitted; Obituaries and SUBJECT FILE, Hungary
    - 1952-1954
    - 1955-1960 (Box 10)
    - 1961-1966
    - 1967-1973
    - Letters of Maurin to various Central and Latin American newspapers regarding their possible publication of Sender's articles, 1953 (arranged alphabetically by newspaper title)
  - Serge, Victor, 1929-1947
  - Serge, Vlady, 1949
  - Serna, Victor de la, 1966
  - Serra, Javier. See Dana Perfumes
  - Serra Llavayol, Martin (Productos Plasticos, Madrid), 1949-1953
  - Serrano Plaja, Arturo, 1961
  - Serrano Poncela. S., 1957-1960
  - Sierra Berdecia, Fernando, 1961
  - Sigurdsson, Halldor -brother of Bella Zagarella-, 1963
  - Silone, Ignazio, 1958-1962
  - El Socialista, Paris, 1949-1952
  - Sociedades Hispanas Confederadas. See Gonzales Malo, Jesus and BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, Obituaries
  - Solano, Wilebaldo, 1947-1965
  - Solari, Juan Antonio, 1962-1965
  - Soto, Osvaldo N., 1967-1968
  - Souchy, Augustin, n.d.
  - Souvarine, Boris, 1930-1965. See also SUBJECT FILE, Unamuno, Miguel de
  - Spanish Communist Party. Executive Committee, 1926
  - Spanish Refugee Aid, Inc., N.Y., 1954-1973. See also Casals, Pablo
  - Stuart, Jozefa, 1961
  - Sudamericana S.A., Buenos Aires, 1949-1966
  - Sunol, Julio C., 1958-1961
  - Tambone, Natalia and Peter, 1966 (Box 11)
  - Tarradellas, Josep, 1960-1971
  - Tasca, Angelo, 1934
  - Tegnell, Geoffrey G., 1971-1972
  - Teide, Barcelona, 1960
  - Tellez, Hernando, 1953-1957
  - Thomas, Hugh, 1961-1963
  - Thomas, Norman. See SUBJECT FILE, Hungary and Scales, Junius
  - Tierno Galvan, Enrique; Llorens, Vicente; Gonzalez Lopez, Emilio, 1962
  - Toller, Ernst, 1932
  - Torre, Guillermo de, 1959
  - Torres, J. Eddy, 1958
  - Le Travail, Geneva, 1934
  - Trejos, Raul F., 1954-1961
  - Trilla, Gabriel Leon, 1925
  - Trotsky, Leon. See SUBJECT FILE, Trotsky, Leon
  - Truman, Harry S., 1951-1953
  - Tuso, Tomas, 1947-1973
  - United Nations Organizations, N.Y., 1947-1972
  - Uslar Pietri, Arturo, 1958. See also BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, Condolences sent to JM
  - Utges, See BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, Condolences sent to JM
  - Vaquero, Carmen and Eloy, 1958-1960
  - Vasconcelas, Jose, 1959. See also SUBJECT FILE, Hungary
  - Vega, Jose de la (Temas, N.Y.), 1952-1971. See also Portas, Rafael E.
  - Vela, David. See SUBJECT FILE, Hungary
  - Velazquez, Juan Luis, 1962
  - Veltrusky, Jiri (Paul Barton), 1955
  - Venegas, Filando, Pascual. See SUBJECT FILE, Hungary
  - Verissimo, Erico (Pan American Union, W.,D.C.), 1956-1958
  - Vidal Rimont, E., 1969
  - Vieira, Alexandre, 1928-1960
  - Viladrich, Alberto, 1956-1972
  - Villar, Manuel -husband of Benigna Galvez-, 1958-1960
  - Villeda Morales, Ramon, 1956-1957
  - Volio Jimenez, Fernando, 1962-1964
  - Volman, Sacha (Institute of International Labor Research, Inc., N.Y.), 1960-1965
  - Wagner, Robert F., 1958
  - Wellington Sears Company, N.Y., 1949
  - Wolfe, Bertram and Ella, 1934-1969. See also SUBJECT FILE, Hungary
  - Yusti, Roberto. See SUBJECT FILE, Hungary
  - Zagarella, Bella -sister of Halldor Sigurds-son-, 1963
  - Zamora A., 1932
  - Zulueta Greenbaum, Carmen de, 1963-1964. See also BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, Condolences sent to JM
  - Zwirn, Jacques, 1969
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, 1918-1973
  - Pre-1948 (Box 11)
    - Untitled, n.d. Handwritten notes on the Acts of the Baleares
    - "El actual momento politico" (The present political moment). Handwritten copy of an article published in Bohemia, September 14, 1933
    - "La actual revolucion espanola" (the present Spanish revolution), n.d. Newspapers accounts of a speech, Ateneo of Madrid
    - "La actual situacion politica" (The present political situation), n.d. Handwritten copy of a speech, Ateneo of Madrid
    - "Adonde va el partido socialista?" (Where is the socialist party going?), n.d. Handwritten copy of an article
    - "Alianza Obrera" (Workers' alliance), n.d. Handwritten copy of an article
    - "Alianza Obrera Antifascista" (Antifascist workers' alliance). Handwritten copy of an article published in Mataro, Aug. 2, 1933
    - "Alianza Obrera contr el Fascismo" (Workers' alliance against fascism). Handwritten copy of an article published in Bohemia, July 28, 1933
    - "Amerique Latine" (Latin America), 1930-1931. 10 typewritten articles on various Latin American countries
    - "El Arte y la Revolucion" (Art and revolution), Jan. 25, 1933. Handwritten copy of an article
    - "Azana: ida y vuelta" (Azana: back and forth), June 18, 1933. Handwritten copy of a speech, Barcelona
    - "Bajo la Dictadura de Primo de Rivera. El Terror Blanco en Espana" (Under the dictatorship of Primo de Rivera. White terror in Spain), Nov. 1928. Four typewritten copies of an essay of 12p.
    - "La Batalla" (The battle), Sept. 22, 1932. Handwritten outline for a speech, premises of the B.O.C.
    - "El Bloque Obrero y Campesino. Origines - Tactica - Perspectivas" (The workers and peasants' bloc. Origins - Tactics - Perspectives), Feb. 7, 1932. Typewritten copy of an essay of 29 p.
    - "El Bloque Obrero y Campesino", Sept. 1, 1934. Typewritten copy of an essay of 44 p.
    - El Bloque Obrero y Campesino, n.d. Handwritten notes
    - "Carlo Marx y el socialismo cientifico" (Karl Marx and scientific socialism), n.d. Typewritten copy of an essay of 13 p.
    - "Cartas de Paris" (Letters from Paris), 1928. 42 typewritten weekly articles written in Paris and published in El Pais, Lerida. See also CORRESPONDENCE, Sarradell, Enrique
    - "Chronique des revues latino-americaines" (Chronicle of Latin American magazines), Oct. 26, 1929. Typewritten copy of an article
    - "La classe ouvriere contre le fascisme. Les Staliniens ont du accepter le front unique" (The working class against fascism. The Stalinists have had to accept the popular front), Sept. 1934. Typewritten copy of an article
    - "El comunismo en Espana" (Communism in Spain), n.d. Handwritten copy of an essay
    - "Controversia Maurin-Campalans" (Controversy Maurin-Campalans), Oct. 16, 1932. Handwritten notes
    - "La crisis mundial del capitalismo" (The world crisis of capitalism), March 4, 1932. Newspapers accounts of a speech, Ateneo Obrero, Turon
    - "La Critica del Programa del Gotha" (The Critique of the Gotha Program), May 1, 1936. Typewritten copy of an article
    - "La decadencia intelectual de la burguesia espanola" (The intellectual decadence of the Spanish bourgeoisie), April (?) 1926. One printed copy of an article; two typewritten copies in Spanish and two in French; one handwritten draft in Spanish (Box 12)
    - "Despues del fallo del Tribunal de Garantias contra la ley de contractos de cultivos" (After the sentence of the tribunal of guarantees against the cultivation laws), n.d. Handwritten copy of a speech, Ateneo Enciclopedico Popular, Barcelona
    - "Deux gouvernements en Espagne" (Two governments in Spain). Typewritten copy of an article published in Folkets Dagblad, July 1934
    - "Diaz Miron", n.d. Typewritten copy of an article
    - "Dictadura de la propriedad agraria" (Dictatorship of the landed property), n.d. Handwritten draft of a chapter for a book
    - "La diferenciacion ideologica dentro de la Confederacion Nacional del Trabajo. Ante una maniobra de los Anarcosindicalistas" (Ideological differences within the national labor federation. Before a maneuver of the anarchosindicalists), Feb. 1926. Printed copy of an article
    - "Dostoievsky: La Casa de los Muertes" (Dostoievsky: The House of the Dead), n.d. Handwritten copy of an essay
    - En las Prisiones de Franco (In the prisons of Franco), written in prison in 1943 and published May 5, 1974.
      - Prologue by German Arciniegas, May 1973. Three typewritten copies
      - One bound typewritten copy of the manuscript, under the original title of Los Siete Circulos (The seven circles)
      - Three typewritten drafts of the manuscript
      - One typewritten draft of the manuscript (Box 13)
      - Typewritten and handwritten copy of the beginning of the first chapter, in French
    - "El entierro de Pablo Iglesias" (The funeral of Pablo Iglesias), Dec. (?) 1925. One printed copy of an article
    - "Espagne" (Spain), series of typewritten articles written in Paris and published in Le Monde
      - January-May 1929, (60 articles)
      - June-December 1929, (87 articles)
      - January-June 1930, (63 articles)
    - "El espiritu del sindicalismo" (The spirit of trade-unionism), Jan. 16, 1920. Notes and handwritten copy of a speech, premises of the Sindicato Unico de Trabajadores, Huesca
    - "Les evenements de l'Amerique Latine" (The events of Latin America), Nov. 8, 1930. One typewritten copy of an article published in Le Monde
    - "Les evenements du Mexique" (The events of Mexico), 1930? One printed copy of an article published in Le Monde
    - "Fascismo y Comunismo" (Fascism and communism), Feb. 24, 1932. Handwritten copy of an article published in La Fuelguera, including research notes
    - "Formacion historica del Estado espanol" (Historical formation of the Spanish state), Jan. 1926. One printed copy of an article published in three parts and one handwritten draft
    - El Fracaso del Anarco-Sindicalismo. La crisis de la C.N.T. (The collapse of anarcho-syndicalism. The crisis of the C.N.T.), 1932? One printed copy of an essay of 48 p. published by J. Horta, Barcelona
    - "El fracaso del sindicalismo reformista" (The collapse of reformist trade-unionism), n.d. One printed copy of an article
    - "Gabriela Mistral", n.d. Two typewritten articles on Gabriela Mistral, one in Spanish and one in French
    - Hacia la Segunda Revolucion (Until the second revolution), 1935. (Box 14)
      - One handwritten copy of the manuscript
      - One typewritten copy of the first chapter
      - One typewritten copy of the second chapter
      - One typewritten copy of the third chapter
      - Various material related to the Spanish edition of 1935 (promotion, reviews, law-suits, correspondence)
      - Various material related to the French edition of 1937 -under the title Revolution et Contre-Revolution en Espagne (Revolution and counter-revolution in Spain), promotion, reviews, correspondence between Mrs. Maurin and the publisher
      - For the Spanish edition of 1966 under the title Revolucion y Contrarrevolucion en Espana, see Post-1948,Revolucion y Contrarrevolucion en Espana
    - Los Hombres de la Dictadura (The men of the dictatorship), 1930
      - Two typewritten copies of the prolog
      - Two typewritten copies of the first chapter on Sanchez Guerra
      - Two typewritten copies of the second chapter on Cambo
      - Two typewritten copies of the third chapter on Pablo Iglesias-Largo Caballero (Box 15)
      - Two typewritten copies of the fourth chapter on Lerroux-Melquiades Alvarez
      - Reviews
    - "Los ideales sociales y la universidad popular" (Social ideas and university for the workers), n.d. Typewritten copy of an essay of 10 p.
    - "Importancia de las huelgas politicas en periodo revolucionario" (Importance of political strikes in a revolutionary period). Printed copy of an article published in La Batalla, March 31, 1934
    - Impressions of Maurin's trip to the Soviet Union. Printed copy of three speeches given at the Ateneo Enciclopedico Popular of Barcelona and published in El Diluvio along with reviews, April 28, May 5 and 11, 1922